Guide to the George B. Hawley Collection MS 011
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
George B. Hawley Collection
1910-1927, (Bulk 1917-1918)
1917-1918
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Hawley, George B., 1895-1918.
MS 011
9.25 Linear Feet, 2 boxes and 2 OS Folders
The collection contains the World War I letters, photographs and miscellanea of George Hawley, a Danbury native who was in Company B of the 307th Infantry of the American Expeditionary Force. Hawley died of disease just before the end of the War in October of 1918.
Provenance
Gifted to the WCSU Archives.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Hawley was born on April 27, 1895, in Danbury. He was the only son of Mr. and Mrs. George M Hawley. He had a sister named Mayme, who was married to an Ivan Fairchild. Hawley spent most of his life in Danbury in the Great Plain district. He worked for several years as a clerk in Barnum pharmacy. About 1916, he left Danbury for Ansonia to work first in a pharmacy and then later as a timekeeper for the Coe Brass Company. On February 18, 1918, he enlisted into the army as a private.
Hawley spent the first part of his training at Camp Devens located near Ayers, Massachusetts, located around one hour from Boston. He was a part of the 23rd Company, 6th Battalion while he was there. It was also there he started his basic training, received his uniform, inoculations, vaccinations and ID number. After about 6 weeks, he was transferred to Camp Upton in Long Island, NY.
Camp Upton was the training camp for Company B of the 307th Infantry where he finished his training and was issued his rifle. While in camp, the division had a group picture taken right before being sent to fight in the war in France.
Hawley was first under fire in northern France in June of 1918 and continued to see battle on several occasions thereafter and his unit was one of the first AEF units to join the lines of battle in France. His division was marched from the northern front to the southern front during which time Hawley kept in constant contact with his family back home. He often wrote to his mother and sister to update them on what he was doing, what or whom he saw, and his experiences in the military. In turn, they would keep in contact with him and updating him as to what was happening on the home front, especially what was going on in Danbury.
During the latter part of 1918, Hawley contracted spinal meningitis and died shortly thereafter on October 7, 1918, at the age of twenty-three.
Scope and Content Note
Most of the collection's contents document Hawley's personality, the relationship he had with - and the effect of the war on - his family, friends, and the community.
This collection is comprised of letters, postcards, copies of clippings, photographs, booklets about the war, certificates, classification cards, memorial service book, a dedication announcement about the who causalities (located in Central Park), and 2 pocket bibles.
There are about seventy letters in this collection. Hawley wrote twenty-eight of these letters to his mother and to his sister and four were written by his mother to him. Other correspondences addressed to his family in regard to his death are from the U.S. Department of War, government agencies, and newspaper articles and included. It should be noted that for seven letters in the collection appear to have been written after Hawley's death. There are fifteen postcards, (eleven of which are from Hawley) dated before he went to war. Photos of Hawley are also in this collection as well as two other soldiers whose identities are still in question. It is believed that they are Louis Peter and George Hinkley, but this has not been confirmed. There are also five photos of Hawley's burial in France and two photos of his regiment. The clippings came mostly from the Danbury Evening News, the Evening Sentinel (Ansonia), and the New York Times. It is believed that some of these clippings were sent to Hawley during the war from family and friends. Dates are written on some of these clippings, but may not be inaccurate.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically and by material type.
The files are grouped into 1 series.
Missing Title
Inventory
Correspondence.; Photographs.; Ephemera.; Argonne, Battle of the, France, 1918; United States -- History -- World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Campaigns; World War, 1914-1918 -- Personal narratives; Danbury (Conn.) -- History.; Hawley Family; Barnum pharmacy.; Coe Brass Company.; Hawley, George B., 1895-1918.; Hawley, Mayme.; United States. Army. American Expeditionary Forces
- Letters written by George Hawley, Feb.28-Sept. 30, 1918
  - From Fort Devens and Camp Upton
    - Letter to George M. and Mary A. Hawley from Fort Devens, Feb 28, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 1)
      General note
      1 page
    - Letter to Mary A. Hawley from Fort Devens, Mar 3, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 2)
      2 pages
    - Letter to Mary (E. Hawley) Fairchild from Fort Devens, Mar 13, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 3)
    - Letter to Mary A. Hawley from Fort Devens, Mar 14, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 4)
    - Letter to Mary A. Hawley from Camp Upton, Mar 19, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 5)
    - Letter to Mary A. Hawley from Camp Upton, Mar 28, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 6)
    - Letter to Mary A. Hawley from Camp Upton, Apr 3, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 7)
    - Letter to Mary A. Hawley from Camp Upton, Apr 5, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 8)
  - From France
    - To Mary E. (Hawley) Fairchild, May 5, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 9)
    - To Mary A. Hawley, May 23, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 10)
    - To Mary A. Hawley, May 30, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 11)
    - To Mary A. Hawley, Jun 1, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 12)
    - To Mary A. Hawley, Jun 19, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 13)
      3 pages
    - To Mary E. (Hawley) Fairchild, Jun 20, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 14)
    - To Mary A. Hawley, Jun 23, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 15)
    - To Mary E. (Hawley) Fairchild, Jun 26, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 16)
    - To Mary A. Hawley, Jul 4, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 17)
    - To Mary E. (Hawley) Fairchild, Jul 6, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 18)
    - To Mary A. Hawley, Jul 10, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 19)
    - To Mary A. Hawley, Jul 16, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 20)
    - To Mary E. (Hawley) Fairchild, Jul 23, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 21)
    - To Mary A. Hawley, Jul 24, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 22)
    - To Mary A. Hawley, Aug 1, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 23)
    - To Mary A. Hawley, Aug 5, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 24)
    - To Mary A. Hawley, Aug 11, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 25)
    - To Mary E. (Hawley) Fairchild, Aug 18, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 26)
    - To Mary A. Hawley, Aug 19, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 27)
    - To Mary A. Hawley, Sep 19, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 28)
    - To Mary A. Hawley, Sep 30, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 29)
- Letters written to Hawley, July 30-Oct. 29, 1918
  - From Mary A. Hawley, Jul 30, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 30)
  - From Mary A. Hawley, Sep 25, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 31)
  - From Mary A. Hawley, Oct 23, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 32)
  - From Mary A. Hawley, Oct 29, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 33)
- Letters written to Hawley's family, May 16, 1918- Jan. 28,1921
  - Allotment Insurance Letter, May 15, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 34)
  - Absentee Ballot Notification, Jun 17, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 35)
  - Soldier's Aid Committee, Jun 30, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 36)
  - Letter to Unknown (possibly George B. Hawley), Aug 19, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 37)
  - Letter to Constance Von Gal, Sep 5, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 38)
  - Mary A. Hawley's Brother in England, Oct 17, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 39)
  - Emerson Publishing Company, Nov 4, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 40)
  - Condolence letter, Von Gal, Constance, Nov 5, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 41)
  - Condolence letter, Nov 7, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 42)
  - Condolence letter, Nov 9, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 43)
  - War Dept.; Adjutant General's Office, Nov 14, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 44)
  - Condolence letter, Nov 23, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 45)
  - Letter re: George M.'s work, Dec 1, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 46)
  - Condolence letter re: George M.'s work, Dec 1, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 47)
  - Condolence letter Odd Fellows, Jan 7, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 48)
  - Office of the Quartermaster, Base section, France, Jan 10, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 49)
  - Danbury War Bureau, Jan 30, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 50)
  - Flint and Smith Publishers, Mar 6, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 51)
  - Condolence letter, [L.S. Bond?], Apr 26, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 52)
  - Mesves Hospital Center, France, May 5, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 53)
  - Office of the Quartermaster - Graves Registration Service, May 12, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 54)
  - Photography of Graves - Graves Registration Service, May 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 55.1)
  - Chief, Effects Bureau, May 15, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 55)
  - 77th Division Association, Jun 2, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 56)
  - Condolence Letter, [L.S. Bond?], Jun 15, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 57)
  - War Department - War Risk Insurance, Jun 16, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 58)
  - War Department - Office of Effects, Jun 20, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 59)
  - 77th Division Association - Employment Bureau, Jul 22, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 60)
  - 307th Infantry - Family Unit, Jul 25, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 61)
  - U.S. Treasury - Claims Dept., Aug 28, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 62)
  - Knights of Columbus (A.E.F.), Oct 1, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 63)
  - Ewing Incorporated Photography, Dec 9, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 64)
  - Soldier's Record Publishing Association, Feb 28, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 65)
  - Discharge Certificate, Jan 28, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 66)
  - Letter from State Library, Jun 6, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 67)
  - Co. B roll call, undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 68)
  - Regimental History, undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 69)
  - Regimental History Forms, undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 70)
  - Order Receipt, undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 71)
  - Soldier's Publishing Record, undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 72)
  - Photo Return Slip, undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 73)
  - War Photos for Sale, undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 74)
- Letters w/ unknown date
  - Thank you, November 15, 19?? (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 76)
  - Condolences, November 22, 19?? (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 77)
  - Thank You; Condolences, undated (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 78)
  - Death Notice, undated (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 79)
  - Hink Letter, undated (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 80)
  - Invitation, undated (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 81)
  - Family Condolence Letter, undated (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 82)
- Photos (5 of Hawley, 5 of his memorial plot in France, and 2 photos of unknown soldiers believed to be his friends)
  - Unidentified soldier's portrait, undated (Box 1, Folder 5, Item 86)
  - Unidentified soldier's portrait, undated (Box 1, Folder 5, Item 87)
  - Fishers Island Postcard, Jun 26, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 5, Item 88)
  - Drill Postcard, Oct 1, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 5, Item 89)
  - Camp Upton Postcard, Mar 26, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5, Item 90)
  - George in Uniform, undated (Box 1, Folder 5, Item 91)
  - KOC Grave in France Photo, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5, Item 92)
  - George before War, undated (Box 1, Folder 5, Item 93)
  - Red Cross photo of Graves in France, undated (Box 1, Folder 5, Item 94)
  - Red Cross photo of George's Grave, undated (Box 1, Folder 5, Item 95)
  - Knights of Columbus photo of George's Grave in France, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5, Item 96)
  - US Graves Registration Service photo of George's Grave in France, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5, Item 97)
  - Red Cross photo frame, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5, Item 98)
- Postcards (11 from Hawley prior to war, 15 overall), 1916-1918
  - Holiday Condolence Card, undated (Box 1, Folder 6, Item 104)
  - Company Address Card, Feb 27, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 6, Item 105)
  - "The Beauty Shop" Postcard, undated (Box 1, Folder 6, Item 106)
  - Christ Church Ansonia Postcard, April 06, 19?? (Box 1, Folder 6, Item 107)
  - Farrell Foundry and Machine Co. Postcard, April 28, 19?? (Box 1, Folder 6, Item 108)
  - Beach Postcard, Jun 26, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 6, Item 109)
  - Mortar Drill Postcard, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 6, Item 110)
  - Industrial Heart of Naugatuck Valley Postcard, Jun 22, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 6, Item 111)
  - Bridgeport Nation Bank Postcard, Jul 6, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 6, Item 112)
  - Mononotto Inn Postcard, Jul 30, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 6, Item 113)
  - Ansonia Episcopal Church Postcard, Aug 22, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 6, Item 114)
  - Ansonia Street view Postcard, Oct 23, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 6, Item 115)
- Miscellaneous
  - Clippings (including obituary, memorial service,Newspaper clippings about the war and Company B), 1918-1921 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - History of Company B, 1920 (book) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Section on CT from Soldiers of the Great War, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Classification Card 1, Feb 1, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10, Item 117)
  - Classification Card 2, Feb 23, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10, Item 118)
  - Dedication Program, May 30, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 10, Item 119)
    4 pages
  - Liberty Bond Pamphlet, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10, Item 120)
    24 pages
  - Memorial Service Program, Nov 17, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10, Item 122)
    5 pages
  - YMCA Mother's Day Pamphlet, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10, Item 123)
    9 pages
  - Warrant Instructions, undated (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 124)
  - Death Notice, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 125)
  - Envelope to Mary A. Hawley, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 126)
  - Envelope to Mary A. Hawley, 1918 (Folder 11, Item 127)
  - Div History order form, undated (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 128)
  - Advertising Pamphlet, undated (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 129)
  - Medallion advertisement, undated (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 130)
- Oversized
  - 2 pocket Bibles, 1910, 1918 (Box OS 1, Item 1, 2)
    One inscribed to Hawley by his pastor in February of 1918 and one by Hawley's friend, Dora Taylor, in 1910.
  - Mailing tubes for photographs and certificates, 1918-1923, undated (Box OS 1, Item 3-6)
  - Certificates (6 items), 1918-1923, undated (Box OS 1, Folder 1)
    Includes:
    Certificate of Valor from State of Connecticut, 1923
    Commemorative Poster inscribed to Hawley (Goddess Columbia)
    Certificates of Honor from the U.S. Dept. of War
  - 4th Regiment, Connecticut State Guard - Photograph, 1918 (Box OS 1, Folder 2)
    Company L, 4th Infantry, CSG. Camp Major Rau, Niantic CT. Brittle condition. 7.5 x 36" b&w
  - U.S. Army, 307th Infantry Regiment - Photograph, 1918 (Folder OS 1)
    Panoramic photo print (7.5 x 60" b&w) of the 307th Infantry Regiment Camp Upton, L.I.. Brittle condition.
  - The Americans in France: War Map of the Western Front, 1918 (Folder OS 2)
    Specifically Indicating Where American Troops are Engaged, 1918